<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-26T16:03:25+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">fiddlybits</title><entry><title type="html">Some Venting About Corpo-speak</title><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/corpo-speak" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Venting About Corpo-speak" /><published>2025-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/corpo-speak</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/corpo-speak"><![CDATA[<p>Fair warning: this post doesn’t really have any technical, aesthetic, or argumentative merit. I just wanted to complain, and complaining in an ostensibly public place does actually work better than the “write it and throw it away” crowd may think.</p>

<p>There are certain phrases that, for reasons I will attempt (and likely fail) to touch on, I find disproportionately, perhaps unreasonably, obnoxious. These excretions are the textual – and really unfortunately, sometimes verbal – equivalent of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corporate_Memphis">Corporate Memphis</a>, both blandly generic and carefully obscure.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Thanks in advance</strong> or <em>*shudder*</em> <strong>TIA</strong>. Like tipping before service is rendered, this phrase has disconnected the acknowledgement from its purpose, making it even more perfunctory than it already was while attempting to pre-emptively excuse yourself when you disrespectfully forget to acknowledge the work that someone has done in response to your <em>ask</em>.</li>
  <li><strong>Ask</strong>. While taking pains to point out that I will avoid the prescriptivist “it’s not a noun” argument, I will say that it still grates in an aesthetic sense. Functionally, it is less precise than several other common words – question, request, demand – which means that it fails miserably on the grounds of being jargon. What is its purpose? To save one syllable so your recipient has to read between the lines to understand the nature and severity of the thing being asked?</li>
  <li><strong>Context</strong> in some… contexts. What’s wrong with “information”? Using “context” where it means “information” makes it sounds like you don’t know what the word means but you want to sound smart, while eroding the usefully unique applications of the word in cases where it does <em>not</em> simply mean “information”.</li>
  <li><strong>Logo</strong> as synecdoche for “company/organization”. I’m not typically one to defend corporations, but there’s something reductively selfish about calling a paying customer, even a heartless megacorporation, a “logo”. Like they are stickers to collect on your water bottle before you forget about them and move onto the next one. Wait, they’re paying customers with legitimate requests and complaints? Sorry, I can’t hear you over my slides full of logos.</li>
  <li><strong>Infinite runway.</strong> Normal people not in the big tech cult would call this “profitability” because, as it turns out, normal businesses need to turn a profit to stick around instead of indefinitely suckling at the teat of venture capitalists. If it’s not profitability, why are you trying to trick me into thinking it is?</li>
  <li><strong>Reach out</strong>. You’re reaching out, but by using this phrase, you’re paradoxically keeping the target at arm’s length. I find this phrase excusable in a corporate context for that reason, but when it leaks into casual speech, I squash it. Your relationship with the reach-out-ee is better described with something like “talk to”, “call”, “text”, “email”, “ask”, “tell”, “request”, “plead” or “yell at”, meaning, as with <em>ask</em>, this phrase fails at jargon and makes your recipient do some guesswork.</li>
  <li><strong>Warm regards</strong>. Pronounced “tepid acknowledgement”, this oddly specific pairing of words is more common than it should be. Just say “thank you” or “see you soon” or literally any other stock phrase that reflects the nature of the preceding message. Emails – which are the environment where this phrase evolved and the only one it continues to inhabit – are not generally “warm”, especially not if your current relationship with the recipient is one where you think this phrase might apply. Don’t make it weird.</li>
</ul>

<p>Now on the other hand, there’s at least one corporate phrase I <em>love</em> to use:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Shareholder value</strong>, which can be used to explain <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/cartoon/a16995"><em>everything</em></a>.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<section class="next-previous">
    
    <a href="/code-style" class="next-previous-link next-previous-previous" title="Previous Post: My Code Style">
      <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span>
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span> Previous Post
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">My Code Style</div>
      </div>
    </a>
     
    <div class="next-previous-placeholder"></div>
    
  </section>
<hr />

<section class="tag-list">
  <i class="tag-label">tags:</i>
  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/opinion">opinion</a> 
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fair warning: this post doesn’t really have any technical, aesthetic, or argumentative merit. I just wanted to complain, and complaining in an ostensibly public place does actually work better than the “write it and throw it away” crowd may think.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Code Style</title><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/code-style" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Code Style" /><published>2025-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/code-style</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/code-style"><![CDATA[<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#what-this-is" id="markdown-toc-what-this-is">What This Is</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#use-engineering-judgement" id="markdown-toc-use-engineering-judgement">Use Engineering Judgement</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#the-underlying-philosophy" id="markdown-toc-the-underlying-philosophy">The Underlying Philosophy</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#data-first-business-logic-second" id="markdown-toc-data-first-business-logic-second">Data First, Business Logic Second</a></li>
      <li><a href="#tools-not-process" id="markdown-toc-tools-not-process">Tools, Not Process</a></li>
      <li><a href="#strive-to-explain-intent" id="markdown-toc-strive-to-explain-intent">Strive to Explain Intent</a></li>
      <li><a href="#write-quality-code-the-first-time" id="markdown-toc-write-quality-code-the-first-time">Write Quality Code the First Time</a></li>
      <li><a href="#perfect-is-the-enemy-of-good" id="markdown-toc-perfect-is-the-enemy-of-good">Perfect is the Enemy of Good</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#superficial-code-style" id="markdown-toc-superficial-code-style">Superficial Code Style</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#consistency" id="markdown-toc-consistency">Consistency</a></li>
      <li><a href="#automated-formatters" id="markdown-toc-automated-formatters">Automated Formatters</a>        <ul>
          <li><a href="#exception-multi-line-regexes" id="markdown-toc-exception-multi-line-regexes">Exception: Multi-line Regexes</a></li>
          <li><a href="#exception-cross-language-byte-identical-find-replace" id="markdown-toc-exception-cross-language-byte-identical-find-replace">Exception: Cross-language, Byte-identical Find-replace</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#comments" id="markdown-toc-comments">Comments</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#when-to-use-comments" id="markdown-toc-when-to-use-comments">When to Use Comments</a></li>
      <li><a href="#examples-of-useful-comments" id="markdown-toc-examples-of-useful-comments">Examples of Useful Comments</a></li>
      <li><a href="#examples-of-extraneous-comments" id="markdown-toc-examples-of-extraneous-comments">Examples of Extraneous Comments</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#naming" id="markdown-toc-naming">Naming</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#names-should-be-at-least-two-words" id="markdown-toc-names-should-be-at-least-two-words">Names Should Be At Least Two Words</a></li>
      <li><a href="#use-standard-vocabulary" id="markdown-toc-use-standard-vocabulary">Use Standard Vocabulary</a></li>
      <li><a href="#avoid-most-abbreviations" id="markdown-toc-avoid-most-abbreviations">Avoid Most Abbreviations</a></li>
      <li><a href="#initialisms-are-words" id="markdown-toc-initialisms-are-words">Initialisms are Words</a></li>
      <li><a href="#functions-should-be-verb-y" id="markdown-toc-functions-should-be-verb-y">Functions Should be Verb-y</a></li>
      <li><a href="#values-should-be-noun-y" id="markdown-toc-values-should-be-noun-y">Values Should be Noun-y</a></li>
      <li><a href="#exception-booleans" id="markdown-toc-exception-booleans">Exception: Booleans</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#managing-state" id="markdown-toc-managing-state">Managing State</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#control-flow" id="markdown-toc-control-flow">Control Flow</a>        <ul>
          <li><a href="#match-if-with-else-whenever-possible" id="markdown-toc-match-if-with-else-whenever-possible">Match <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code> with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">else</code> Whenever Possible</a></li>
          <li><a href="#use-assertions-to-supplement-types" id="markdown-toc-use-assertions-to-supplement-types">Use Assertions to Supplement Types</a></li>
          <li><a href="#combine-and-eliminate-cases" id="markdown-toc-combine-and-eliminate-cases">Combine (and Eliminate) Cases</a></li>
          <li><a href="#explicit-alternatives" id="markdown-toc-explicit-alternatives">Explicit Alternatives</a></li>
          <li><a href="#branch-in-the-right-place-or-inline-and-factor-out" id="markdown-toc-branch-in-the-right-place-or-inline-and-factor-out">Branch in the Right Place (or: Inline <em>and</em> Factor Out)</a></li>
          <li><a href="#functions-decide-or-act-not-both" id="markdown-toc-functions-decide-or-act-not-both">Functions Decide <em>or</em> Act, Not Both</a></li>
          <li><a href="#use-exhaustiveness-checking" id="markdown-toc-use-exhaustiveness-checking">Use Exhaustiveness Checking</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><a href="#variable-scope" id="markdown-toc-variable-scope">Variable Scope</a>        <ul>
          <li><a href="#dont-store-derived-values" id="markdown-toc-dont-store-derived-values">Don’t Store Derived Values</a></li>
          <li><a href="#defer-declarations-as-late-as-possible" id="markdown-toc-defer-declarations-as-late-as-possible">Defer Declarations as Late as Possible</a></li>
          <li><a href="#shorten-lifetimes-with-blocks-or-one-use-functions" id="markdown-toc-shorten-lifetimes-with-blocks-or-one-use-functions">Shorten Lifetimes with Blocks (or One-use Functions)</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><a href="#mutation-and-side-effects" id="markdown-toc-mutation-and-side-effects">Mutation and Side Effects</a>        <ul>
          <li><a href="#prefer-constant-variables" id="markdown-toc-prefer-constant-variables">Prefer Constant Variables</a></li>
          <li><a href="#minimize-mutations-blast-radius" id="markdown-toc-minimize-mutations-blast-radius">Minimize Mutations’ Blast Radius</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#types" id="markdown-toc-types">Types</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#enumerations-v-booleans" id="markdown-toc-enumerations-v-booleans">Enumerations v. Booleans</a></li>
      <li><a href="#keyword-arguments" id="markdown-toc-keyword-arguments">Keyword Arguments</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#debuggability-and-observability" id="markdown-toc-debuggability-and-observability">Debuggability and Observability</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#string-literal-log-lines" id="markdown-toc-string-literal-log-lines">String Literal Log Lines</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#version-control-ie-git" id="markdown-toc-version-control-ie-git">Version Control (i.e. Git)</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#squash-v-rebase-v-merge-into-mainline" id="markdown-toc-squash-v-rebase-v-merge-into-mainline">Squash v. Rebase v. Merge into Mainline</a></li>
      <li><a href="#force-pushingrebasing-feature-branches" id="markdown-toc-force-pushingrebasing-feature-branches">Force-pushing/Rebasing Feature Branches</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="what-this-is">What This Is</h1>

<p>This is my code style. “Style” here means how concepts are represented, structured and explained to the reader, not where I put the curly brackets.</p>

<p>There is no objectively correct answer regarding this kind code of style, but this document outlines the main pillars of mine. As such, they are also the things I look for in code reviews. I refer to this document when doing code reviews (which is probably why you’re here).</p>

<p>Yes, this document is very dry.</p>

<h2 id="use-engineering-judgement">Use Engineering Judgement</h2>

<p><strong>None of these points on style are hard and fast.</strong> They overlap and sometimes trade off. Ultimately, code needs to serve an end, and sometimes that requires compromising on principles.</p>

<h1 id="the-underlying-philosophy">The Underlying Philosophy</h1>

<p>Before wading into the crossfire on when and how to write comments, I want to outline some more abstract concepts that are reflected in the more-specific opinions that follow.</p>

<p>The philosophical points below are idealistic and can’t always be achieved within in the constraints of any given code review, but I strive for them when possible.</p>

<h2 id="data-first-business-logic-second">Data First, Business Logic Second</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Show me your flowcharts [algorithms] and conceal your tables [data model], and I shall continue to be mystified. Show me your tables, and I won’t usually need your flowcharts; they’ll be obvious.</p>

  <p>– Fred Brooks, Mythical Man Month</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If you don’t know what values you’re operating with, you can’t do anything with them. The names, types and lifetimes of values, as well as the interaction between them, should be the primary driver for how code is structured. Programs are ultimately machines for processing inputs into outputs, so build around those inputs and outputs and any necessary intermediates.</p>

<h2 id="tools-not-process">Tools, Not Process</h2>

<p><em>a.k.a.</em> <strong>Solve Problems Once</strong></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you haven’t automated your last-year self out of a job, you aren’t learning.</p>

  <p>– An ex-manager of mine (paraphrased)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Don’t do manually what can be done automatically. Put the work in now to find, configure or build the right tool for the job, then never think of that problem again. Don’t make anyone else have to think about the problem, either, if you can avoid it: documentation is no replacement for automation.</p>

<h2 id="strive-to-explain-intent">Strive to Explain Intent</h2>

<p>Code is an unambiguous, precise specification of behavior, so treat it like one. Computers don’t need to have code explained to them, but people do. Write your code so it’s clear what you <em>intend</em> to have happen, so that when it inevitably doesn’t, someone besides you – or just your future self – can understand how to fix it properly.</p>

<p>This supersedes the oft-cited “don’t be clever”: removing or avoiding cleverness is common result of striving to explain intent.</p>

<h2 id="write-quality-code-the-first-time">Write Quality Code the First Time</h2>

<p>Spend the time now to save the time later.</p>

<p>If I sent you this page, you aren’t the first employee of an underfunded startup in do-or-die mode. Every corner you cut will be paid for dozens of times over with every reader of your code. Bike shed your names before you merge. Your prototype <em>will</em> end up in production, so give it a little more thought.</p>

<h2 id="perfect-is-the-enemy-of-good">Perfect is the Enemy of Good</h2>

<p>The standard phrasing of this – “don’t let perfect be the enemy of good” – isn’t assertive enough for my tastes. You are in control. Misguidedly seeking perfection isn’t happening <em>to</em> you.</p>

<p>What’s usually missed when this is cited is that (1) it takes a lot experience to learn where the line is and (2) where you draw the line is probably not exactly where I do. Keep this in mind and learn to be a little flexible without compromising on the principles that truly make a difference.</p>

<h1 id="superficial-code-style">Superficial Code Style</h1>

<p>A quick diversion into what “style” usually means to state some core high-level principles. We’re still not talking about curly brackets.</p>

<h2 id="consistency">Consistency</h2>

<p>Whoever said “consistency is the hobgoblin of little minds” never had to work in a multi-million line codebase. Rather, it is a tool of the practitioner, not a fetish of the theoretician.</p>

<p>Consistency is how you can do massive code reviews and not trip over every line (such reviews <em>do</em> happen: sorry idealists).</p>

<p>Consistency enables quick and dirty regexes when you can’t rely on types to find usages.</p>

<p>Consistency is why I can use inconsistency to draw attention to unavoiably peculiar code.</p>

<p>Consistency is how I stay sane.</p>

<h2 id="automated-formatters">Automated Formatters</h2>

<p>Automated formatters like Prettier and Black are to be considered correct, <em>even in weird edge cases</em>. When there is a conflict on style, the automated formatter is correct. Modern bikesheds come pre-painted. Spend your valuable time elsewhere.</p>

<h3 id="exception-multi-line-regexes">Exception: Multi-line Regexes</h3>

<p>Regexes are always hard to read. Unfortunately, long regexes are sometimes necessary. In the case where you cannot comment on a long nasty regex by pointing to <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/201323/how-to-validate-an-email-address-using-a-regular-expression">some documentation</a> (or your language doesn’t have <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/regexbuilder"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RegexBuilder</code></a> <em>*swoon*</em>), it’s probably a good idea to break your regex up onto multiple lines and explain what each piece is doing.</p>

<p>In this case, automated formatters are likely to wreck your significant indentation or inline sections that were separated for clarity and should therefore be disabled if they do not understand your multi-line regex.</p>

<h3 id="exception-cross-language-byte-identical-find-replace">Exception: Cross-language, Byte-identical Find-replace</h3>

<p>Some languages have syntactic overlap, but often have differing formatting rules. In the <em>exceptionally rare</em><sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> circumstances where it’s valuable to have the same sequence of characters across two languages, disable the formatter for that block.</p>

<h1 id="comments">Comments</h1>

<p>Comments should be used to explain <em>why</em>, not <em>what</em> and definitely never <em>how</em>.</p>

<p>This section refers only to regular comments, not doc comments, which serve an entirely different purpose.</p>

<h2 id="when-to-use-comments">When to Use Comments</h2>

<p>Sparingly.</p>

<p>Code should strive to be self-explanatory. It is a precise specification of behavior covering both the <em>what</em> and the <em>how</em> by definition, and usually the <em>why</em> by virtue of naming, organization and common contextual knowledge (i.e. what the whole program is designed to do).</p>

<p>Comments are suitable only when there is no reasonable naming or organization of the code that can address the <em>why</em>. Explaining <em>what</em> or <em>how</em> risks the comment becoming misleading in the future, since comments are not checked for consistency or sanity by any automated tool. Misleading comments are worse than no comments. Don’t litter.</p>

<h2 id="examples-of-useful-comments">Examples of Useful Comments</h2>

<p>Useful comments are those that explain necessary but unusual code constructs, such as those that:</p>

<ul>
  <li>are hacks</li>
  <li>have magic constants</li>
  <li>have non-obvious side-effects</li>
  <li>work around weird APIs</li>
  <li>satisfy some automated tool, such as a linter</li>
  <li>intentionally preserve style for compatibility or historical reasons</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="examples-of-extraneous-comments">Examples of Extraneous Comments</h2>

<p>Common occurences of unjustifiable comments are those that:</p>

<ul>
  <li>explain an inline constant
    <ul>
      <li>Instead, hoist it to a SHOUTING_CASE value, and if it still needs explanation, then consider a comment.</li>
      <li>In the specific cases of numbers or strings, it can sometimes be useful to break the derivation of the value out into steps for emphasis, e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">const FIFTEEN_MINUTES = 15 * 60 * 1000;</code></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>explain a boolean parameter at a call site
    <ul>
      <li>Instead, consider <a href="#enumerations-v-booleans">rewriting the called function to accept an enumeration</a> (or keyword arguments), forcing the call site to be clearer.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>restate adjacent code in prose
    <ul>
      <li>Instead, delete the comment.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="naming">Naming</h1>

<p>Good names go a long way towards pre-empting reader questions and code comments. Following certain conventions makes the code-reading experience smoother by not surprising your reader. They can even speed up code-writing by forcing you to stop and think <em>“What exactly am I trying to express here?”</em> rather than barging ahead into a dead end with whatever control flow first comes to mind.</p>

<h2 id="names-should-be-at-least-two-words">Names Should Be At Least Two Words</h2>

<p>The clarity of any given name goes <em>way</em> up from one word to two. Look around you: how many tables, chairs, windows, devices, utensils, tools, vehicles or people can you uniquely identify in your current “scope” by adding just one adjective or locator to, well, “table”, “chair”, “window”, etc.? When in doubt, overshare.</p>

<p><strong>Exception:</strong> in highly-generic contexts, you might not be able to come up with a better name than <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">row</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data</code>.</p>

<p><strong>Exception:</strong> in inline contexts, shorter names can improve clarity by reducing repetitive noise, such as in e.g. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">all_entries.filter(e =&gt; e.enabled)</code>.</p>

<h2 id="use-standard-vocabulary">Use Standard Vocabulary</h2>

<p>Prefer well-known words like “get” rather than synonyms like “obtain”. Use boring, clear names almost all the time. While fun, your code should require neither a dictionary nor a thesaurus. Unusual names suggest unusual behavior, so don’t be misleading.</p>

<p><strong>Exception:</strong> don’t be afraid to use jargon when it’s suitable. If you’re overloading the subtraction operator, it’s okay, even preferred, to say “subtrahend”.</p>

<p><strong>Exception:</strong> if you want to define something new with <em>very particular and maybe unusual</em> semantics, it can be useful to choose a word that doesn’t have baggage and define it to mean what you want. Consider leaving a comment.</p>

<h2 id="avoid-most-abbreviations">Avoid Most Abbreviations</h2>

<p>Your editor has autocomplete and your ability to parse streams of letters is not the bottleneck to your understanding. Don’t be afraid of <em>authentication</em>, <em>rasterization</em> or even <em>canonicalization</em>.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> It’s better to spend the extra milliseconds now and avoid ambiguity and confusion later.</p>

<p>If you really want to abbreviate things, only do it if they are at least one of:</p>
<ul>
  <li><em>common in English</em>, such as “appt” for “appointment”</li>
  <li><em>obvious in context</em>, such as referring to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mag</code> of a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Vector3</code></li>
  <li><em>idiomatic</em>, such as looping with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">i</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">j</code></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="initialisms-are-words">Initialisms are Words</h2>

<p>Treat initialisms and acronyms as words for the purposes of casing. Don’t write <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AWSIAMJSONParser</code>; write <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AwsIamJsonParser</code>. I hope this example is self-explanatory. (If not, how about <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">JPEGEXIFGPSLookup</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">XMLDTDURIResolver</code>?)</p>

<p>As a bonus, some tools (e.g. IntelliJ) have built-in fuzzy-search behavior that returns higher-quality results when initialisms are capitalized as words.</p>

<h2 id="functions-should-be-verb-y">Functions Should be Verb-y</h2>

<p>Action words like “get”, “commit” or “write” communicate that a function <em>performs an action</em>. This re-emphasizes the distinction between code and data (hi, Lispers!) along with your language’s syntax and the syntax highlighter, and helps frame the naming question in useful terms: what does this function <em>do</em>?</p>

<h2 id="values-should-be-noun-y">Values Should be Noun-y</h2>

<p>Variables and parameters should have noun-y names that communicate <em>what</em> role they play, but rarely <em>how</em>. Avoid including the type of the variable in its name, which may change and thereby confuse more than help. Like functions being verb-y, this emphasizes a distinction and helpfully frames the question to aid in picking a good name.</p>

<h2 id="exception-booleans">Exception: Booleans</h2>

<p>Empirically, boolean functions and values benefit from some special considerations. They should be phrased…</p>
<ul>
  <li><em>declaratively</em>, like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">is_something()</code> rather than <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">check_if_something()</code>.</li>
  <li><em>positively</em>, e.g. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">is_something_enabled</code>, not negatively, e.g., <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">is_something_disabled</code>. This reduces indirection by one level and helps avoid unnecessary double negatives.</li>
</ul>

<p>Consider <a href="#enumerations-v-booleans">replacing boolean values by a two-state enumeration</a>.</p>

<h1 id="managing-state">Managing State</h1>

<p>In most run-of-the-mill programming, the complexity you and your reader have to deal with comes from having to track three things:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>control flow</strong> paths, in order to understand all the possible paths through a piece of code</li>
  <li><strong>variable scopes</strong>, in order to understand what values are currently in play and could interact with each other</li>
  <li><strong>mutations</strong> made to a value after it is initially declared, changing how it may interact with other values or control flow constructs</li>
</ul>

<p>Designing your code in order to reduce the size of the state space introduced by these three things can significantly reduce the surface area for bugs and make the code easier to both read and write.</p>

<p>All three of these have overlap with each other and with <a href="#types">types</a>, so I have tried to assign each pattern to the context it interacts with the most.</p>

<h2 id="control-flow">Control Flow</h2>

<p>Reduce the number of possible paths control can take through a given piece of code (the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyclomatic_complexity">cyclomatic complexity</a>). Ideally, this means eliminating branches entirely.</p>

<h3 id="match-if-with-else-whenever-possible">Match <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code> with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">else</code> Whenever Possible</h3>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code> blocks without <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">else</code>s often look like a mistake. The entire rest of the scope is still controlled by the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code>, but implicitly. If you must use a standalone <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code>, spend the space saying <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">else { /* noop */ }</code> so there is no doubt. Fall-through in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">switch</code> is widely disliked and usually only permitted with an explanation or at least acknowledgement; this is little different.</p>

<p>Many <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code>s-without-<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">else</code>s are early returns. If these are grouped at the top of a function, they are permissible, but they will often be better expressed by one of the constructs described in the next sections, such as <a href="#use-assertions-to-supplement-types">assertions</a> or <a href="#combine-and-eliminate-cases">eliminating redundant cases</a>.</p>

<p>Early returns anywhere but at the top of a function are usually more surprising than helpful, and should be avoided if the function is more than a loop or two.</p>

<p>Avoiding lone <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code>s has the added benefit of being able to more reliably use indentation as a reminder and emphasis for which statements are subject to which control flow.</p>

<h3 id="use-assertions-to-supplement-types">Use Assertions to Supplement Types</h3>

<p>Not all valid inputs can be expressed in the type system. Assertions are a clear and compact expression of those preconditions which cannot be. They should be phrased positively – “this must be true to continue” not “if this is not true, stop” – and are necessarily declarative in style.</p>

<p>Standalone <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code>s whose body is a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">throw</code>/<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">raise</code> are assertions in disguise, but phrased in reverse and introducing additional unnecessary scopes.</p>

<h3 id="combine-and-eliminate-cases">Combine (and Eliminate) Cases</h3>

<p>All techniques for eliminating branches boil down to identifying cases which appear distinct, but are not. Essentially distinct things often manifest as distinct types, and cannot be handled the same way. If you have multiple cases handling values of the same type, look closer: the cases may be more similar than they first appear. Finding a way to combine them might reveal an underlying truth and a correspondingly more elegant solution.</p>

<p>A very common case of unnecessarily distinct cases is nullable collection types. Is a null array a meaningfully distinct thing from an empty one? Usually, not: in both cases, you are going to do zero iterations. Use an empty array, and unconditionally iterate, instead of null checking.</p>

<h3 id="explicit-alternatives">Explicit Alternatives</h3>

<p>If one branch being hit means that other branches cannot be, represent that explicitly.</p>

<p>A series of three independent <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code>s in a row doing is-instance checks will not all trigger for a given value, but at a skim (and perhaps without strong compiler support) this may not be obvious. Three <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code>s represent 8 possible paths. By chaining <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code>s into <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">else if</code>s, you can reduce the number of paths in this example to 3 or 4 (depending on if the last case is a catch-all or not).</p>

<p>This technique can often be used to great effect inside loop bodies that would otherwise have to be written with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">break</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">continue</code>.</p>

<h3 id="branch-in-the-right-place-or-inline-and-factor-out">Branch in the Right Place (or: Inline <em>and</em> Factor Out)</h3>

<p>Moving a branch higher or lower in the control flow can make a huge difference.</p>

<p>In an extreme case, consider the difference between a set of related methods (say, some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Create,_read,_update_and_delete">CRUD</a>) that can handle two kinds of entities. You would almost certainly rather have eight methods bundled into two sets of four (two entites times four CRUD methods), than four methods, each containing one branch per entity type.</p>

<p>This can go the other way, too: sometimes readability is improved if you drop an entire <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">if</code>-<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">else</code> construct and replace it with a single ternary, buried deep in some otherwise-consistent expression.</p>

<p>In both cases, the goal is to find that crossover point that minimizes both the number of branches, and the number of <em>kinds</em> of branches (or things that are being branched on).</p>

<p>When considering functions specifically, this manifests as the decision to inline or factor out a function body. Inlining can eliminate redundancy such as large parameter sets, whereas factoring out can reduce variable scopes, and both can eliminate control flow redundancy in surrounding code.</p>

<h3 id="functions-decide-or-act-not-both">Functions Decide <em>or</em> Act, Not Both</h3>

<p>One generally thinks of a function as code that effects a change to something, but oftentimes the complexity instead comes in <em>choosing</em> which change to make. Unless one or both of “decide” and “act” are simple, split them into separate functions, perhaps even one-use functions. This almost always yields a very clear separation of concerns that can be effectively tested and might enable some deduplication (e.g. multiple decisions that end up acting the same).</p>

<p>You may have to introduce a new type if the decision cannot be represented as a primitive type. This is often a blessing in disguise; this new type will likely make it easier to identify which cases are meaningfully distinct and may point the way to a simpler implementation of either or both of the “decide” or “act” phases.</p>

<p>In rare cases, making this change and noticing that many decisions boil down to the same act with tiny variations can lead to noticing that <em>all</em> decisions boil down to the same act, which removes the “decide” part entirely.</p>

<h3 id="use-exhaustiveness-checking">Use Exhaustiveness Checking</h3>

<p>Instead of carefully inspecting whether every input type has as corresponding branch, make the type checker do it. Many languages have first-class exhaustiveness checking (<a href="https://gibbok.github.io/typescript-book/book/exhaustiveness-checking/">1</a>, <a href="https://rustc-dev-guide.rust-lang.org/pat-exhaustive-checking.html">2</a>, <a href="https://docs.swift.org/swift-book/documentation/the-swift-programming-language/controlflow/#Switch">3</a>…), so when you modify your type, which is the source of truth for what your code is capable of, the language ensures all usages are up-to-date.</p>

<p>Exhaustiveness checking is so useful that I routinely reshape or augment existing types specifically so that they can fit the language’s preferred style for it. This falls under “solve all problems once”. Yes, I am an admitted <a href="https://brooker.co.za/blog/2020/06/23/code.html">type system maximalist</a>.</p>

<h2 id="variable-scope">Variable Scope</h2>

<p>Try to reduce the number of ways variables could potentially interact with each other. Ideally, this means eliminating a variable entirely.</p>

<p>Every declared variable is another item to keep track of. The larger the scope of the variable, the longer one has to remember what the value is for and what changes, if any, the value has undergone since its declaration. Longer-lived variables also overlap with more other variables, increasing the number of possible interactions an unfamiliar reader has to consider.</p>

<h3 id="dont-store-derived-values">Don’t Store Derived Values</h3>

<p>Storing values derived from other values requires careful management of the derived value to ensure it is consistent with the inputs. This is a form of cache invalidation, which is a known <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/TwoHardThings.html">hard thing</a>.</p>

<p>Instead, compute them on the fly when needed by the end consumer. Many languages have good, idiomatic ways to do this, like JavaScript closure-thunks, Java getters, and Python properties.</p>

<h3 id="defer-declarations-as-late-as-possible">Defer Declarations as Late as Possible</h3>

<p>A variable declaration is a statement to your reader: “here, keep an eye on this”. If you declare everything up front in your scope, you have maximized the number of possible interactions to consider. If you declare a variable without initializing it, you have most likely put your program into a temporarily-invalid state (that you presumably intend to resolve near-immediately).</p>

<p>Declaring variables closer to where they are used reduces possible interactions and likely gives you the opportunity to provide a useful initialization value.</p>

<h3 id="shorten-lifetimes-with-blocks-or-one-use-functions">Shorten Lifetimes with Blocks (or One-use Functions)</h3>

<p>Anonymous scoping blocks (if your language supports it) or one-use functions (otherwise) can be used to move the end of a variable’s lifetime earlier. This complements moving the declaration later to minimize possible interactions with other variables. In cases where several intermediate values are juggled to produce some other value, an anonymous block can ensure those intermediate values can be forgotten about by the reader as soon as the block ends, rather than hang over their head through the rest of the function.</p>

<p>Some languages make this more ergonomic than others. Languages with blocks-as-values are best; languages whose only scope control is functions are acceptable, but one has to get used to the idea of breaking out single-use functions.</p>

<h2 id="mutation-and-side-effects">Mutation and Side Effects</h2>

<p>Try to reduce the number of possible states your program can be in. Ideally, values can be initialized once and never changed.</p>

<h3 id="prefer-constant-variables">Prefer Constant Variables</h3>

<p>In languages that support it, declaring variables constant (heh) is recommended in all cases where it’s possible. The majority of modern application glue code is not a performance bottleneck, and making the computer go slightly out of the way to compute and store a series of constants is rarely going to harm scalability.</p>

<p>Constants are both easier for a human to reason about, and may allow compilers and other tools to make optimizations under the hood to reclaim any lost performance. In extreme cases, code without mutation may run faster than faster-looking mutation-based code because optimizations like vectorization become possible.</p>

<h3 id="minimize-mutations-blast-radius">Minimize Mutations’ Blast Radius</h3>

<p>Where mutation cannot be avoided for practical reasons, encapsulate it in a (testable!) implementation where consumers can mostly or entirely ignore the grisly details. In many languages, this is a perfect application of classes, which can hide all intermediate/book-keeping values away from the consumer and only allow known-good operations at the right times. See also: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/State_machine">state machines</a>.</p>

<p>Functional-like programming is increasingly prevalent in historically-imperative languages. This is a Good Thing, and means that classes can be reserved as a signpost saying “here be dragons”, rather than a Java-style code organization catch-all.</p>

<h1 id="types">Types</h1>

<p>This section is general recommendations for types that do not fit in a narrower context.</p>

<p>See also <a href="#use-exhaustiveness-checking">exhaustiveness checking</a>.</p>

<h2 id="enumerations-v-booleans">Enumerations v. Booleans</h2>

<p>Booleans are a two-valued enumeration. Some languages make compilation decisions based on which you choose, but by and large which to use is a stylistic decision.</p>

<p>Nullable booleans should be avoided. They are a three-valued enumeration, where the null value has potentially-unclear or even accidental semantics and depending on the language/database/protocol support for null handling, may be an unnecessary footgun. Consider a user-controlled setting: does null mean “use the default at the time I close the settings page” or “use the default at the time the setting is used”? Instead of answering that question directly, either explicitly default the boolean at write time or define an enumeration with a member called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">use_current_default</code> (respectively).</p>

<p>Boolean parameters should be used sparingly, as many call sites with boolean literals are reader-unfriendly. This is extra true if there are multiple boolean parameters.</p>

<h2 id="keyword-arguments">Keyword Arguments</h2>

<p>Functions with many parameters are sometimes unavoidable. Mitigate the readability difficulty and ordering sensitivity by using keyword arguments, so the call sites are clearer to read and easier to write correctly.</p>

<p>In some languages this may require you to define a new type. These types often end up as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union_type">union types</a>, since it’s rare that every parameter in a large parameter list is used in every code path, which may point to a beneficial refactor to split the methods or even re-combine the different paths (and corresponding parameters) back together.</p>

<p>Keyword arguments can even amplify the readability of good names where they are not strictly necessary to mitigate large parameter lists, as seen frequently in Swift.</p>

<h1 id="debuggability-and-observability">Debuggability and Observability</h1>

<h2 id="string-literal-log-lines">String Literal Log Lines</h2>

<p>Log lines should have a (hopefully unique) string literal explaining their purpose. Pass relevant values in a separate parameter.</p>

<p>Interpolating relevant values into the primary log message makes it difficult for a human to quickly grep for the log’s source, introduces unnecessary formatting uncertainty (do you quote string-type values? what if the string has a quote in it? what if your string is the word “null”?) and can make it difficult or impossible for logging tools to extract and search/aggregate on those values.</p>

<h1 id="version-control-ie-git">Version Control (i.e. Git)</h1>

<p>With apologies to Mercurial, Perforce, Fossil, and (extra apologies) SVN/CVS users.</p>

<h2 id="squash-v-rebase-v-merge-into-mainline">Squash v. Rebase v. Merge into Mainline</h2>

<p>Between squashes and merges I prefer merges, but <em>consistency</em> is more important. If your team uses squashes, you must permit an escape hatch for occasional merges. Rebasing is never correct, both lying about development history while still cluttering it with non-“atomic” commits.</p>

<p>Consistency across the team means I always know where to go to get the development history of a change – either in-repo or the code review tool – and I can write/use automated tooling knowing what to expect. Mixing styles makes every dive into code history an unpleasant surprise.</p>

<p>Squash-based workflows must have an escape hatch for true merges to deal with scripted changes. This is for a few reasons:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The script should <em>always</em> be present in the history nearby the change it made, but it’s likely undesirable to have it in the repo right now.</li>
  <li>The automated changes may be uninteresting for e.g. blame, and Git supports mechanisms to ignore named commits for blames and diffs.</li>
  <li>When debugging the change in the future, it is important to know if the issue originated in automated changes or related manual changes.</li>
</ul>

<p>Squashing fails at all three.</p>

<h2 id="force-pushingrebasing-feature-branches">Force-pushing/Rebasing Feature Branches</h2>

<p>Depends on the current state of the code review and quality of the review tools.</p>

<p>If nobody has reviewed your code, force-pushing is acceptable, and possibly even desirable in order to present the best-organized history to the first reviewer(s).</p>

<p>If a review is in progress, force-push only if the review tools support it in a first-class way. At the time of writing GitHub completely shits the bed, losing comments and unsetting review state all over the place, which is a huge waste of time for reviewers. A competitor I have used and like, <a href="https://reviewable.io">Reviewable</a>, supports force-pushes first-class and will show your reviewer the actual diff, even from a commit they saw previously that is no longer on the branch.</p>

<hr />

<section class="next-previous">
    
    <a href="/yogurt" class="next-previous-link next-previous-previous" title="Previous Post: Yogurt Recipe">
      <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span>
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span> Previous Post
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">Yogurt Recipe</div>
      </div>
    </a>
     
    <a href="/corpo-speak" class="next-previous-link next-previous-next" title="Next Post: Some Venting About Corpo-speak">
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          Next Post <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">Some Venting About Corpo-speak</div>
      </div>
      <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
    </a>
    
  </section>
<hr />

<section class="tag-list">
  <i class="tag-label">tags:</i>
  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/programming">programming</a>,  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/reference">reference</a> 
</section>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Useful cross-language byte-identical find-replace has happened exactly once in my programming life (both professional and personal), but I want this document to be complete, so it’s included. I wanted to find exact matches across JavaScript and JSON files, but JSON only permits double-quotes while JavaScript’s Prettier formatter was configured for single quotes. Notably, the tool with this code was later rewritten to something simpler and more expressive such that maintaining formatting consistency became irrelevant (and impossible), which is the ideal outcome. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I tried to come up with non <em>-tion</em> words, but those nounified verbs come up all the time! <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="programming" /><category term="reference" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Yogurt Recipe</title><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/yogurt" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yogurt Recipe" /><published>2025-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/yogurt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/yogurt"><![CDATA[<!-- Only show unit switcher if js is enabled: hide by default. -->
<p><span id="unit-switcher-wrapper" style="display: none">
  Units: 
  <a href="#" id="unit-switcher-metric">metric</a>
   • 
  <a href="#" id="unit-switcher-imperial">stupid</a>
</span></p>

<p>Makes as much yogurt as milk you put in. Scales up or down indefinitely.</p>

<p>In addition to the ingredients, you’ll need one or more containers equalling the volume of milk you use, an ice bath, and a sous vide machine (or a few towels).</p>

<p>If you use a sous vide machine, this recipe will require about 4 hours of fermentation. Make sure the containers are tall enough or seal tightly enough that they will not leak into the bath.</p>

<p>If you do not use a sous vide machine, the recipe will probably require more than 4 hours of fermentation, and the final product will likely be thinner. You may also want to start the fermentation <span class="unit metric">3°C</span><span class="unit imperial">5°F</span> hotter, to keep the yogurt cultures in their preferred temperature range for longer (but not too hot!).</p>

<p>You can reculture some store-bought yogurts, as long as they specify they have live cultures, which you can find in both cheap and expensive yogurts.</p>

<hr />

<p>Heat</p>

<ul>
  <li><span class="unit metric">2 liters</span><span class="unit imperial">½ gallon</span> whole milk</li>
</ul>

<p>in a pot over medium heat until it reaches <span class="unit metric">95°C</span><span class="unit imperial">200°F</span>, stirring frequently to minimize scalding, and skimming off the skin as necessary.</p>

<p>Prepare an ice bath for the milk. Chill, stirring frequently to ensure even cooling, until it reaches <span class="unit metric">45°C</span><span class="unit imperial">110°F</span>.</p>

<p>Add</p>

<ul>
  <li><span class="unit metric">125ml</span><span class="unit imperial">½ cup</span> yogurt</li>
</ul>

<p>to a small bowl. Spoon approximately <span class="unit metric">50ml</span><span class="unit imperial">¼ cup</span> of milk into the yogurt, stirring to combine, then repeat a couple more times until the yogurt is warmed and diluted.</p>

<p>Pour the yogurt mixture back into the milk pot, and stir thoroughly.</p>

<p>If you’re using a sous vide machine, set it to <span class="unit metric">45°C</span><span class="unit imperial">110°F</span>. Divide the milk mixture into your containers, and put them in the sous vide bath. Sous vide for 4 hours.</p>

<p>If you are not using a sous vide machine, leave the milk mixture in the pot and wrap it completely with towels. Set it in a warm place in the kitchen for at least 4 hours.</p>

<p>The yogurt is done when it reaches your desired consistency and tartness. Longer fermentations will thicken the yogurt (to a limit) and make it more tart. Remember that cold yogurt is thicker! If you want to make Greek yogurt, strain through cheesecloth or a fine mesh strainer until your desired consistency is reached.</p>

<hr />

<section class="next-previous">
    
    <a href="/hummus" class="next-previous-link next-previous-previous" title="Previous Post: Hummus Recipe">
      <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span>
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span> Previous Post
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">Hummus Recipe</div>
      </div>
    </a>
     
    <a href="/code-style" class="next-previous-link next-previous-next" title="Next Post: My Code Style">
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          Next Post <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">My Code Style</div>
      </div>
      <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
    </a>
    
  </section>
<hr />

<section class="tag-list">
  <i class="tag-label">tags:</i>
  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/recipe">recipe</a> 
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="recipe" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Units:  metric  •  stupid]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hummus Recipe</title><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/hummus" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hummus Recipe" /><published>2025-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/hummus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/hummus"><![CDATA[<!-- Only show unit switcher if js is enabled: hide by default. -->
<p><span id="unit-switcher-wrapper" style="display: none">
  Units: 
  <a href="#" id="unit-switcher-metric">metric</a>
   • 
  <a href="#" id="unit-switcher-imperial">stupid</a>
</span></p>

<p>One recipe makes approximately <span class="unit metric">1 liter</span><span class="unit imperial">1 quart</span> of hummus.</p>

<p>Combine:</p>

<ul>
  <li>1 clove of garlic (or 2 if you want a bite)</li>
  <li><span class="unit metric">530 grams</span><span class="unit imperial">3 cups</span> drained chickpeas, liquid reserved</li>
  <li><span class="unit metric">60 grams</span><span class="unit imperial">¼ cup</span> lemon juice</li>
  <li><span class="unit metric">60 grams</span><span class="unit imperial">¼ cup</span> reserved chickpea liquid or water</li>
  <li><span class="unit metric">70 grams</span><span class="unit imperial">¼ cup</span> tahini</li>
  <li><span class="unit metric">110 grams</span><span class="unit imperial">½ cup</span> olive oil</li>
  <li><span class="unit metric">½ tsp (2 grams)</span><span class="unit imperial">½ tsp</span> table salt</li>
</ul>

<p>in a food processor. Process for 5 minutes, scraping down sides if necessary. Thin out with more chickpea liquid as desired.</p>

<p>Garnish with any or none of chopped parsley, paprika or sumac.</p>

<hr />

<section class="next-previous">
    
    <a href="/ebonizing" class="next-previous-link next-previous-previous" title="Previous Post: Notes on Ebonizing Wood">
      <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span>
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span> Previous Post
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">Notes on Ebonizing Wood</div>
      </div>
    </a>
     
    <a href="/yogurt" class="next-previous-link next-previous-next" title="Next Post: Yogurt Recipe">
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          Next Post <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">Yogurt Recipe</div>
      </div>
      <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
    </a>
    
  </section>
<hr />

<section class="tag-list">
  <i class="tag-label">tags:</i>
  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/recipe">recipe</a> 
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="recipe" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Units:  metric  •  stupid]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes on Ebonizing Wood</title><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/ebonizing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Ebonizing Wood" /><published>2025-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/ebonizing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/ebonizing"><![CDATA[<p>Ebonzing wood is the process of putting a black finish on woods by wetting them with an iron solution, which reacts with tannins in the wood to turn black. I referenced two guides:</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="https://timberbiscuitwoodworks.com/blog/how-to-ebonize-wood">Timber Biscuit Woodworks</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.popularwoodworking.com/finishing/ebonizing_wood/">Popular Woodworking</a></li>
</ol>

<p>Both are good, but the former felt easier to follow to me. Here are my notes:</p>

<p>Two cups of distilled white vinegar and half a pad of #0000 steel wool took two weeks to stop reacting and settle on a color remarkably like black tea (after I strained it out). I should have started earlier. It’s possible that more iron would make a solution that performs “better” in some fashion, but I didn’t try.</p>

<p>Yes, spring for the quebracho powder/extract. I bought <a href="https://www.vandykestaxidermy.com/BKT2-P3850.aspx">the one from Van Dyke’s</a> one of the guides linked, which was about $30 all-in. (They have a weird shipping-cost policy… it is not $0 as it appears.) Despite supposedly being one of the more tannic woods, my white oak turned at best a pallid grey without help. I also tried oversteeping cheap black tea to make an undrinkably astringent (i.e. tannic) brew before using the bark extract, but it barely made a difference.</p>

<p>The ebonized layer is thin and the ebonizing solutions themselves are water-thin, so plan your glue-up/sanding/finishing accordingly. I would not recommend more than burnishing or fine steel wool once the ebonizing is done. If you’re doing ebonized accent pieces, you may need to do your sanding/glue-up out of order to avoid accidentally ebonizing adjacent wood, because the solutions <em>will</em> bleed.</p>

<p>Make sure you get into the deep grain, if your chosen wood has it. My first pieces had a lot of completely un-ebonized white grain streaks, which looked bad. I didn’t do any formal side-by-side testing, but some combination of (1) two coats (of each solution, alternating), (2) using steel wool to lightly rub in the iron solution and (3) a drop of dish soap to break the surface tension allowed me to get a consistent black throughout on white oak. Guide #1 above recommends also sanding and then repeating the whole process, but I didn’t try that. (Maybe next time I’ll try those three separately and see which actually helps.)</p>

<p>Use a squirt bottle or pour the solutions into cups/trays. Because this finish is two-part, you don’t want to get one part into the other! All of your applicators will turn the same dark grey/black by the time you’re done, which you don’t want to happen to your entire supply of the solutions.</p>

<p>You may end up with a slightly splotchy dark grey, but once you put the final finish on the workpiece it should all turn a deep, even black. Check out the pictures below.</p>

<p><strong>Test, test, test!</strong> Variances in wood, application technique, brewing up the solution… there’s a lot of variables which you don’t want to learn about the hard way on your almost-finished workpiece.</p>

<hr />

<p>Here’s a few pictures from the process.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/ebonizing/old-test.jpeg" alt="Test pieces from before I tried the bark powder. You can see on the second from the bottom that the end grain is much more consistent and receptive, but on the face grain the color is at best a medium grey. After it sat out for a week it started to turn orange where I had attempted multiple coats, presumably from unreacted rust." />
  <figcaption>Test pieces from before I tried the bark powder. You can see on the second from the bottom that the end grain is much more consistent and receptive, but on the face grain the color is at best a medium grey. After it sat out for a week it started to turn orange where I had attempted multiple coats, presumably from unreacted rust.</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/ebonizing/quebracho-only.jpeg" alt="White oak with only quebracho bark tea on it. This gives you a sense of what it looks like before the ebonizing reaction." />
  <figcaption>White oak with only quebracho bark tea on it. This gives you a sense of what it looks like before the ebonizing reaction.</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/ebonizing/dried.jpeg" alt="Ebonizing solution applied and mostly dried. Notice that it's more dark grey than black, and it's a bit splotchy -- this won't be a problem. This picture was about 30 minutes after the previous, and most of that time was just waiting for it to dry to reveal the true color." />
  <figcaption>Ebonizing solution applied and mostly dried. Notice that it's more dark grey than black, and it's a bit splotchy -- this won't be a problem. This picture was about 30 minutes after the previous, and most of that time was just waiting for it to dry to reveal the true color.</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/ebonizing/finished.jpeg" alt="My finished piece: a side table with accented edges. I used three coats of warm gloss wipe-on polyurethane." />
  <figcaption>My finished piece: a side table with accented edges. I used three coats of warm gloss wipe-on polyurethane.</figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
  <img src="/assets/ebonizing/close-up.jpeg" alt="Close-up of the finished edge. The black is deep and consistent, even though the unfinished ebonized wood was not. The deep oak grain is still very much visible and tactile." />
  <figcaption>Close-up of the finished edge. The black is deep and consistent, even though the unfinished ebonized wood was not. The deep oak grain is still very much visible and tactile.</figcaption>
</figure>

<hr />

<section class="next-previous">
    
    <a href="/edinburgh-recommendations" class="next-previous-link next-previous-previous" title="Previous Post: Edinburgh Recommendations">
      <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span>
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span> Previous Post
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">Edinburgh Recommendations</div>
      </div>
    </a>
     
    <a href="/hummus" class="next-previous-link next-previous-next" title="Next Post: Hummus Recipe">
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          Next Post <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">Hummus Recipe</div>
      </div>
      <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
    </a>
    
  </section>
<hr />

<section class="tag-list">
  <i class="tag-label">tags:</i>
  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/reference">reference</a>,  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/woodworking">woodworking</a> 
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reference" /><category term="woodworking" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ebonzing wood is the process of putting a black finish on woods by wetting them with an iron solution, which reacts with tannins in the wood to turn black. I referenced two guides:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Edinburgh Recommendations</title><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/edinburgh-recommendations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Edinburgh Recommendations" /><published>2025-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/edinburgh-recommendations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/edinburgh-recommendations"><![CDATA[<p>First things first: <em>edin-burruh</em>. That way people know what you’re talking about. Second things second: it’s “whisky”, not “whiskey”.</p>

<p>At the time of writing it’s been four years since I went to Edinburgh, so the list has slimmed down quite a bit from what it might have been due to cognitive attrition. Anyway, in no particular order:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong><a href="https://www.rabbies.com/en-us/tour/loch-ness-inverness-the-highlands-2-day-tour-from-edinburgh">Rabbie’s overnight Highlands tour</a>:</strong> got a great whirlwind tour hitting Inverness, Ben Nevin, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Culloden">Culloden</a>, <a href="https://www.duncarronmedievalvillage.com/">Duncarron</a>, and the largest full Scottish breakfast I’ve ever seen (at a real bed and breakfast)! Ask me about coracles sometime.</li>
  <li><strong>Teutchers Landing:</strong> lovely local pub in an amusingly cobbled-together building and a great selection of scotches.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="https://smws.com/venues/28-queen-street-edinburgh">Scotch Malt Whisky Society (Queen Street)</a>:</strong> their whole thing is you order whisky based purely on the tasting notes – they will not tell you what distillery or whisky it is. Love it.</li>
  <li><strong>Auchentoshan:</strong> okay this is actually in Glasgow, but the train ride is quick because Edinburgh and Glasgow are a conurbation and it’s the nearest notable distillery and offers tours. The tours are great and come with a really interesting tasting at the end.</li>
  <li><strong>Arthur’s Seat:</strong> a mild hike located right in the city with nice views. Great for sunset.</li>
  <li><strong>Haggis:</strong> the weirdness of haggis is way overblown. I think Americans are just afraid of off-cuts. If anything, it’s actually kind of boring – but give it a try anyway just to know.</li>
  <li><strong>Cullen skink:</strong> classic dish that’s basically fish chowder. Not bad if you’re into that kind of thing.</li>
  <li><strong>Harry Potter walking tour</strong> (or just Victoria Street and Greyfriars Kirkyard Cemetery): honestly you could just look it up on the internet and do it yourself… even as a mild Harry Potter fan it’s still kind of interesting to see the subtle or not-so-subtle references made to Edinburgh in the book.</li>
  <li><strong>National Museum of Scotland:</strong> Celts, Anglo-Saxons, and a surprising amount of Industrial Revolution (given the size of the country).</li>
  <li><strong>Fringe Festival:</strong> I haven’t gone, but it sounds like a ton of fun. You’ll probably know if you are accidentally going when it’s on because of the prices of everything.</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Slàinte mhath!</em><sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<hr />

<section class="next-previous">
    
    <a href="/london-recommendations" class="next-previous-link next-previous-previous" title="Previous Post: London Recommendations">
      <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span>
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span> Previous Post
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">London Recommendations</div>
      </div>
    </a>
     
    <a href="/ebonizing" class="next-previous-link next-previous-next" title="Next Post: Notes on Ebonizing Wood">
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          Next Post <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">Notes on Ebonizing Wood</div>
      </div>
      <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
    </a>
    
  </section>
<hr />

<section class="tag-list">
  <i class="tag-label">tags:</i>
  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/recommendations">recommendations</a> 
</section>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I’ll be nice: you should definitely look up the pronunciation of this before you say it out loud to a Scot. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="recommendations" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First things first: edin-burruh. That way people know what you’re talking about. Second things second: it’s “whisky”, not “whiskey”.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">London Recommendations</title><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/london-recommendations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="London Recommendations" /><published>2025-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/london-recommendations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/london-recommendations"><![CDATA[<p>I &lt;3 London, so let’s not dally.</p>

<h3 id="first-up-pubs">First Up: Pubs</h3>

<p><em>The most important.</em> Ask me for my pub list. (I’ll write a blog post for it eventually.)</p>

<h3 id="second-non-food-things">Second: Non-food Things</h3>

<p>In no particular order.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Regent’s canal walk and Thames river walk:</strong> good way to see a bunch of different neighborhoods, and everyone likes water features.</li>
  <li><strong>Portobello Road market:</strong> huge antiques-ish market, with an endless selection of silver in particular.</li>
  <li><strong>Highgate Cemetery:</strong> actually really cool architecture and some interesting history. Very close to Hampstead Heath, which is a particularly nice big park, among all their great big parks.</li>
  <li><strong>Globe Theater:</strong> yeah, touristy, but it’s hard to go wrong with Shakespeare… though there are so many shows to choose from (like The Burnt City, which is the same troupe that did Sleep No More).</li>
  <li><strong>British Museum:</strong> obviously, but specifically, the Sutton Hoo exhibit. Also the Rosetta stone is also just like, right there in the hallway.</li>
  <li><strong>Victoria and Albert Museum (V&amp;A):</strong> ironwork, fashion, plaster casts… it’s interesting and high quality stuff you won’t find in the British Museum.</li>
  <li><strong>London Transport Museum:</strong> if you’re into buses ‘n’ shit. I liked it.</li>
  <li><strong>Parks:</strong> the Brits are good at parks, so if you’re out for a walk, try to route through one of the big ones nearby (there are a lot of those).</li>
  <li><strong>Literally any historic tour:</strong> I did Parliament, the Tower of London, and Hampton Court, all of which were a good time, especially the first one.</li>
  <li><strong>Sunset drinks:</strong> the Shard and the Walkie Talkie have sunset drinks on their top floors.</li>
  <li><strong>St Pancras station</strong> (just if you’re nearby): it’s reaaaally pretty, and King’s Cross is not, which is why the Harry Potter movies lied and used it for filming instead of the real King’s Cross.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="third-food-things">Third: Food Things</h3>

<p>Please note that I am not a Restaurant Person. London is like NYC or LA in this domain – they have literally everything, somewhere, and it’s good. You could very well just find a listicle and not be led too far astray.</p>

<p>Also, British food isn’t as bad as people make it out to be, mostly because they’ve figured out how to make it better and also because <em>you have to expect the right thing</em> – all British food is, basically, fall/winter comfort food. They don’t eat fresh things.</p>

<p>Anyway:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>SUNDAY ROAST:</strong> yes, it’s actually only available on Sundays, and yes, you have to go to a pub to eat it, but no, you don’t even have to order a pint. Check the pub list for recommendations.</li>
  <li><strong>Borough Market:</strong>  a little touristy, but lots of good food choices (including a guy who sells straight sea urchin that I went to several times).</li>
  <li>Postcard Teas: small, fancy tea store with curated and actually interesting collection of teas, plus tastings (though sign up way in advance if you want to do that).</li>
  <li><strong>Bone Daddies:</strong> ramen, in particular, the dipping ramen which I’ve never seen anywhere else, and the Soho one is the original.</li>
  <li><strong>Pick &amp; Cheese:</strong> sushi belt cheese. Also nearby the famous Neal’s Yard Dairy so you can just… buy cheese. To eat.</li>
  <li><strong>Dishoom:</strong> the Indian restaurant on every “best Indian in London” list. It is good, though.</li>
  <li><strong>Lahore Kebab House:</strong> recommended by Meera Sodha in <a href="https://msmarmitelover.com/2017/01/in-conversation-with-meera-sodha-andre.html">this interview</a> (and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210801031009/http://meerasodha.com/where-to-eat/uk/">previously on her site</a>). Was excellently delicious, but the next day was not so great.</li>
  <li><strong>Gunpowder:</strong> also recommended by Meera Sodha. Trendy and and a little fusion-y.</li>
  <li><strong>Abeno:</strong> okonomiyaki/teppanyaki place right next to the British Museum.</li>
  <li><strong>Savory pie,</strong> in general: the one I would have recommended had the chef die (!) while I was there last. (I don’t know if this is the same thing as a hand pie.)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="last-and-certainly-least-anti-recommendations">Last and Certainly Least: Anti-recommendations</h3>

<p>Don’t do these.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Battersea:</strong> the hip new converted-coal-power-plant-development thing. It’s just a mall, though the building itself is really impressive. You can get a similar effect from the Tate Modern, also an ex-power-plant, which is more worth seeing (if you like modern art).</li>
  <li><strong>Changing of the guard:</strong> it’s just some dudes in silly hats marching around. I wouldn’t even bother taking a look at Buckingham Palace unless you’re in the area, since it’s just another European king’s house which are all rather same-y.</li>
  <li><strong>Camden Market:</strong> probably cooler in the past, but mostly just an outdoor punk-hipster mall.</li>
  <li>Leicester Square, Piccadilly Circus: just straight-up tourist traps.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<section class="next-previous">
    
    <a href="/mtg-constructed" class="next-previous-link next-previous-previous" title="Previous Post: Why Constructed, Not Commander">
      <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span>
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span> Previous Post
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">Why Constructed, Not Commander</div>
      </div>
    </a>
     
    <a href="/edinburgh-recommendations" class="next-previous-link next-previous-next" title="Next Post: Edinburgh Recommendations">
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          Next Post <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">Edinburgh Recommendations</div>
      </div>
      <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
    </a>
    
  </section>
<hr />

<section class="tag-list">
  <i class="tag-label">tags:</i>
  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/recommendations">recommendations</a> 
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="recommendations" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I &lt;3 London, so let’s not dally.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Constructed, Not Commander</title><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/mtg-constructed" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Constructed, Not Commander" /><published>2025-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/mtg-constructed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/mtg-constructed"><![CDATA[<p>Hello fellow dork. If you’re here, I probably sent you because you nagged me to play Commander. But I don’t like Commander, and here’s why.</p>

<p><strong>The board states are massively overcomplicated.</strong> I <em>do</em> like intricate multi-hour Euro games, but that’s not the itch that Magic scratches for me. I think Magic is at its best when games are quick and spunky and where the opponents bring clearly-distinct styles, like tennis. The ~400 unique cards in a Commander game dramatically amplify the complexity that Wizards keeps adding<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> when compared to the ~40 unique cards in a Constructed game.</p>

<p><strong>Games quickly become crude, swingy slugfests.</strong> Board wipes followed by dumping huge sorceries (or whatever) using stacks and stacks of lands, mana value be damned. Lurching between different piles of cards is inelegant and loses out on all the fun subtleties in navigating a well-built deck between your opponent’s swings to land a fatal blow. Hitting your curve perfectly and outracing your opponent with 3 life remaining is much more rewarding than crushing them with an overwhelming force of eleven 9/9 tramplers while you sit at 39 life.</p>

<p><strong>Board wipes as the one-size-fits-all solution to all problems is unfun.</strong> It’s unfun from a deckbuilding perspective, since it’s yet another formulaic must-have a la Command Tower. It’s more unfun to play against since, with three opponents, you have to eat a lot of board wipes – not all of which will be even aimed at you – and repeatedly restart from near-zero before you can finally get your game plan online. Board wipes are an expensive commitment in Constructed, so removal is typically more surgical. Plus, being one-on-one, you don’t get caught in any crossfire from someone else looking threatening.</p>

<p><strong>I don’t like politicking and managing social dynamics.</strong> In Commander, I avoid knocking someone out of a game early even if that’s the right strategy because it sucks when that happens to you. You don’t generally have to worry about peoples’ feelings in Constructed. (I also can’t stand Diplomacy.)</p>

<p><strong>Like the much-loathed companion cycle, a commander negatively warps deckbuilding around it.</strong> A lot of decks feel like random in-color cards that are good with the commander and bad without it. Decks with single points of failure (success?) are antithetical to my deckbuilding style, which is also a big part of the reason I don’t like combo decks or tutors.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> I want, and build, decks with lots of little synergies so that there’s always something available, but not the same thing every time.</p>

<p><strong>The decks take a <em>long</em> time to hone.</strong> To be clear, I still spend a lot of time refining my Constructed decks, but you can get a working first draft pretty quickly. In a Constructed deck, substituting even a single playset will often change the feel of a deck noticeably in a way that keeps the feedback loop rewarding and lets you explore more adjacent playstyles without being held back by the required interactions with (or color restrictions of) the commander.</p>

<p><strong>Old cards are ugly.</strong> There, I said it. (To be fair, a lot of new card frames are downright hideous and/or completely unreadable. At least the old cards are consistent and usable, but I’d prefer neither.)</p>

<p>Last time I tried to build a Commander deck, I ended up throwing out the 80% of it that was chaff, and kept the 20% that was fun. And then I put in 4 copies of each card. Oops.</p>

<hr />

<section class="changelog">

  <p><em>Updated 2025-11-16: added comments on board wipes.</em></p>

</section>
<hr />

<section class="next-previous">
    
    <a href="/sideloading-iphone-apps" class="next-previous-link next-previous-previous" title="Previous Post: A Primer on Sideloading Your Own iPhone Apps">
      <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span>
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span> Previous Post
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">A Primer on Sideloading Your Own iPhone Apps</div>
      </div>
    </a>
     
    <a href="/london-recommendations" class="next-previous-link next-previous-next" title="Next Post: London Recommendations">
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          Next Post <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">London Recommendations</div>
      </div>
      <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
    </a>
    
  </section>
<hr />

<section class="tag-list">
  <i class="tag-label">tags:</i>
  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/opinion">opinion</a> 
</section>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>There’s nothing inherently wrong with increasing the complexity of the game, if it’s done tastefully. But recently Wizards has started adding a lot of state to manage, some of which doesn’t have a good physical representation. Exert is one such mechanic (how many times I have accidentally untapped an exerted thing…), and good luck remembering the 4,000 different types of behaviors available to cards in exile depending on how they got there. All of this before we even get to Wizards printing new sets at <em>breakneck</em> speed with some straight-up shitty mechanics, then having the gall to “reprint” the set <em>while it’s being printed for the first time</em> because Daddy Hasbro is too cheap to shell out for all the rights to Spiderman. Fuck you, Hasbro. (Note that this should not be taken to mean I would prefer more Spiderman cards. Universes Beyond is fucking awful, and I’ve hamstrung my own decks a few times just to avoid some of the more egregious crossovers.) <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>My rule of thumb is that any interaction that only happens when three cards are present should be considered pure bonus upside, perhaps shading into win-more, and not required for the deck to work. (Unless one of them is lands, since they are always around.) Three-card interactions are often too fragile to be fun or end up with the deck being a tedious tutor/control/delay shell around those three cards. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hello fellow dork. If you’re here, I probably sent you because you nagged me to play Commander. But I don’t like Commander, and here’s why.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Primer on Sideloading Your Own iPhone Apps</title><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/sideloading-iphone-apps" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Primer on Sideloading Your Own iPhone Apps" /><published>2025-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/sideloading-iphone-apps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/sideloading-iphone-apps"><![CDATA[<p>This (brief) tutorial is for anyone with a Mac who wants to make iPhone apps for personal use<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> but doesn’t want to subject themselves to Apple’s lengthy and capricious publishing process (while paying $100 for the privilege)<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> or deal with jailbreaking.</p>

<h3 id="caveats">Caveats</h3>

<ul>
  <li>You can only do this for 3 apps at a time.</li>
  <li>You have to put your phone into “developer mode”, which Apple describes in vaguely threatening language regarding security.</li>
  <li>You need to leave something running on your computer and be on the same network as it at least one a week.</li>
</ul>

<p>Alternately, you could just move to the EU or lobby your congressperson to get off their fucking asses and do something useful instead of vomiting something about “innovation” and “small businesses” while sucking off a billionaire.</p>

<h3 id="the-actual-tutorial">The Actual Tutorial</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Install <a href="https://altstore.io/#Downloads">AltServer</a> on your computer and AltStore on your iPhone. <a href="https://faq.altstore.io/altstore-classic/how-to-install-altstore-macos">Details.</a>
    <ul>
      <li>You probably want to enable the AltServer &gt; Launch at Login menu option.</li>
      <li>If you can’t see your phone in Finder after unplugging it, try Apple menu &gt; Force Quit… &gt; Finder &gt; Relaunch.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Build an unsigned <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.ipa</code> bundle using Xcode (as far as it’s willing to help).
    <ol>
      <li>Product &gt; Archive (in Xcode 16), which should open the Xcode Organizer showing the build.</li>
      <li>Right-click the build and Show in Finder to reveal the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.xcarchive</code>. It’s a directory, so pop it open (right-click &gt; Show Package Contents, or just <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cd</code>) and find the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.app</code> under <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Products/Applications</code>.</li>
      <li>Pull the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.app</code> out and plop it in a new empty directory somewhere called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Payload</code>.</li>
      <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">zip -r &lt;app&gt;.ipa Payload</code> to finish the unsigned bundle.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Get the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.ipa</code> onto your phone somehow.
    <ul>
      <li>Apple makes this really fucking annoying to do through the Files app,<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> so I just used my Dropbox. iCloud Drive (and other similar things) probably also work.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>In AltStore, go to My Apps &gt; + &gt; navigate to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.ipa</code>.
    <ul>
      <li>Note that it starts you down a directory – hit the back button to see other file systems.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>That should be it! You can test the wireless refreshing by tapping “7 Days” in the newly-installed app listing.</p>

<hr />

<section class="next-previous">
    
    <a href="/bad-drivers" class="next-previous-link next-previous-previous" title="Previous Post: A Refined Theory of Bad Drivers">
      <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span>
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span> Previous Post
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">A Refined Theory of Bad Drivers</div>
      </div>
    </a>
     
    <a href="/mtg-constructed" class="next-previous-link next-previous-next" title="Next Post: Why Constructed, Not Commander">
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          Next Post <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">Why Constructed, Not Commander</div>
      </div>
      <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
    </a>
    
  </section>
<hr />

<section class="tag-list">
  <i class="tag-label">tags:</i>
  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/reference">reference</a>,  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/programming">programming</a> 
</section>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>You can do this trivially in stock Xcode… for 7 days at a time. We grovel at your feet for your magnanimity, oh Grand High Beancounter Tim Cook. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Short version of my stance on app store gatekeeping, since I can’t resist: Apple can and should provide an official distribution channel with tight rules <em>in addition to</em> allowing other app stores and drag-and-drop app installation. There is merit in walled gardens, but the 30% fee (or <a href="https://www.axios.com/2025/05/01/apple-epic-lawsuit-app-store-offsite-fees">27%</a>, yeah, fuck you too, Tim Cook) in absence of competition is (literally) extortionate, their “reviews” seem to let plenty of scams and low-quality garbage through anyway, and these policies stifle small-time operators.<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I would feel stupid that I can’t figure out how to just… move a file onto my iPhone, but I’m pretty sure this is Apple being purposely obstructive. The Files tab in Finder can only drop files into apps that register themselves as file-using, rather than the general Files area. AirDropping an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.ipa</code> is a black hole, I guess either because it’s a blacklisted file type or it’s not a whitelisted file type. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I finally finished an iOS app on the third try in as many years, but I almost gave up again on the way there. The blame for <em>every</em> nontrivial frustration and roadblock is laid squarely at the feet of Xcode or the App Store – <em>never</em> the iPhone itself, the iPhone SDK, or Swift/SwiftUI. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reference" /><category term="programming" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This (brief) tutorial is for anyone with a Mac who wants to make iPhone apps for personal use1 but doesn’t want to subject themselves to Apple’s lengthy and capricious publishing process (while paying $100 for the privilege)2 or deal with jailbreaking. You can do this trivially in stock Xcode… for 7 days at a time. We grovel at your feet for your magnanimity, oh Grand High Beancounter Tim Cook. &#8617; Short version of my stance on app store gatekeeping, since I can’t resist: Apple can and should provide an official distribution channel with tight rules in addition to allowing other app stores and drag-and-drop app installation. There is merit in walled gardens, but the 30% fee (or 27%, yeah, fuck you too, Tim Cook) in absence of competition is (literally) extortionate, their “reviews” seem to let plenty of scams and low-quality garbage through anyway, and these policies stifle small-time operators.[^4] &#8617;]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Refined Theory of Bad Drivers</title><link href="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/bad-drivers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Refined Theory of Bad Drivers" /><published>2025-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/bad-drivers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.sea.nkelley.me/bad-drivers"><![CDATA[<p>Everyone likes to claim that the drivers where they come from are the worst, but we can’t all be right. I think the problem is that we’re talking past each other: there are different ways to be a bad driver.</p>

<p>I hereby propose a rating system with three axes:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>incompetence</strong></li>
  <li><strong>negligence</strong></li>
  <li><strong>aggression</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>Here are some example applications for some places I’m familiar with:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>NorCal:</strong> incompetent and negligent, but emphatically passive</li>
  <li><strong>Italy:</strong> hyper-aggressive, but by and large competent and usually attentive</li>
  <li><strong>New York City:</strong> all sliders to <em>maximum</em></li>
</ul>

<p>I think disagreements happen when your bad drivers and their bad drivers are at even moderately-different positions along these axes.</p>

<p>Interestingly, while it’s obvious that minimal incompetence and minimal negligence is objectively good, the same is not true for aggression. Drivers that are too passive cause traffic flow problems and annoy other drivers – rightfully, I’d say, if you won’t pull into the intersection on green when you’re waiting to turn left.</p>

<hr />

<section class="next-previous">
    
    <a href="/its-all-greek-to-me" class="next-previous-link next-previous-previous" title="Previous Post: It's All Greek to Me">
      <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span>
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          <span class="next-previous-icon">←</span> Previous Post
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">It's All Greek to Me</div>
      </div>
    </a>
     
    <a href="/sideloading-iphone-apps" class="next-previous-link next-previous-next" title="Next Post: A Primer on Sideloading Your Own iPhone Apps">
      <div class="next-previous-name">
        <div class="next-previous-label">
          Next Post <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
        </div>
        <div class="next-previous-title">A Primer on Sideloading Your Own iPhone Apps</div>
      </div>
      <span class="next-previous-icon">→</span>
    </a>
    
  </section>
<hr />

<section class="tag-list">
  <i class="tag-label">tags:</i>
  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/opinion">opinion</a>,  
  <a class="tag-link" href="/tag/theory">theory</a> 
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><category term="theory" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Everyone likes to claim that the drivers where they come from are the worst, but we can’t all be right. I think the problem is that we’re talking past each other: there are different ways to be a bad driver.]]></summary></entry></feed>